and they said welcome back and today is
the last part of distributed logging. So
if you have not seen part one, part two,
part three, kindly check it out first
because we have discussed level
hierarchy, appenders,
a sync, uh appenders and also structured
logging which is JSON and that's where
now we have come till MDC. So everything
is linked. So I would highly recommend
kindly check it out
pre-erequest parts and then we would be
able to link better. Okay. But if you
already know all this topics, we are
good to go. So what is MDC? It is mapped
diagnostic context. So in logging
framework this plays a very very
critical role right in and very critical
role because because of this only I
would say that we are able to achieve
distributed logging. Okay we'll we'll
show you how. So one very important is
it's per thread key value map. So this
MDC is nothing but a map key value. So
key value but it's per thread for every
thread there is only one key value map
exist. Okay. So always remember this per
thread. So MDC.put you put a key and the
value
logging framework log back log 4j2 can
automatically read and attach the key
value to log events. This is the most
important part because of this only
we get like or I would say that why MDC
is very critical because all the logging
framework like log back log 4j can
automatically read this map or the data
present inside this map.
So here if you see that let's say in
your code you have put mdc.put output
certain key payment id and the value and
you have does the log dot info certain
event you are trying to log so what
happen is you know that one of the
implementation so this is SL4j
interface
SL4j interface info okay dot info so
there would be some implementation in
which is present inside either logback
or log 4j 2 so this is an
implementation. What it does is it will
convert your log statement
into
log event which is nothing but a i
logging event. You can say that it's an
object. Okay, it will convert into i
loging event
and in the i loging event there is a
field called mdc property map. So
this property this mdc do.put output
whatever the value we have kept into the
MDC that you can say that it is copied
of this event. Okay. So every event
every whatever you are doing log dot
info log dot error log do anything. So
one event is created which is nothing
but a when I say event means I logging
event object. So for this also it will
create I logging event object. For this
also it will create ie logging event
object. For each log statement one event
is created. Then inside this event
object there is an statement MDC
property map that is filled with
whatever the data present inside your
MDC.
Okay. So now your event has this MDC
value. Now there's a level check. Yes.
Okay. This is this log should be
accepted or rejected depending upon the
logger level. We have already discussed
that. Okay. If your logger level is
let's say info. So all the log
statements uh with info or above level
would be accepted. So this is let's say
info it would be accepted. Then
ultimately it goes to the appender where
we have formatter uh like normal pattern
or through JSON encoder. We have already
seen that. That's where you can see that
another advantage comes into that is
that
they have a proper understanding how to
read this MDC this MDC property map.
So in the formatting whether you are
doing a JSON automatically whatever the
data you are putting into the MDC that
will also get appended into your JSON.
Okay. So currently you are just putting
log.info info payment is successful. So
yes in the JSON you already have message
payment is successful and whatever the
data you have in the MDC that will also
come MDC data will also come. Similarly
in the P pattern if you are not using
JSON if you are using just plain text
pattern there also it is possible that
your MDC whatever the data is present
into the MDC that can come here okay
because I logging event has that info
and over this appenders
whether you are using logback or log 4j2
can automatically read and attach the
key value to the log events ultimately
the output
they can attach
So here just see an example this will
get little bit more clear. If you find
it little bit confusing here like what
exactly happened see this one. So here I
have written an appender
you can give any name the class is
console appender means the output where
the output will go console.
Okay now the encoder so I am using
pattern. So it would be like a plain
text. So the format is date level logger
level info logger name the message and
here if you see I'm using percentage x
so this percentage x is like whatever
the data all the data present inside
your mdc that would be showed up okay so
percentage x is like to fetch all mdc
data so it will come as like key one
equals to value one okay so here our
let's say key is like payment ID so it
would become as like payment id equals
to 1 2 3 something like that if you have
more comma
whatever the let's say another key is
user ID u 1 2 3 something like this will
come so percentage x means print or read
all the values of the MDC and add it
separated
but if you are only interested in one
specific value of the MDC then inside a
pattern return like percentage x and in
the placeholder you give the key name
itself. So what would happen is only for
this key
this value would get ultimately printed
into the log event.
So is to fetch a specific MDC key value.
Please note only value for the specific
key comes not payment ID this key name
will not come only its value will come.
Okay. So here one thing I wanted to show
you that
even though I am just doing log.info
how come our appender during formatting
able to access the MDC data? You got it
right? Because when this log.info is
converted to i loging event, this field
get filled up. Whatever the MDC data we
have that is filled into there and the
formatting works on this i loging event
only because
this event only we have to format it. So
it has access to this MDC property map.
Okay. So we have the MDC data present
and we are just using it with percentage
X. So percentage X is to read all the
MDC data. Percentage X and the
placeholder is for a specific key if you
wanted to read from the MDC data
and in structured JSON. Okay, we have
already seen structured JSON by default
MDC field access is true. So here if you
see now my appender whatever the name
you want to give you can give the class
I'm using is console appender means on
the console the output will go
now the format of the output would be
like the event would be I am using
encoder log-enccoder which is for JSON
okay and include MDC true generally if
you don't write it by default it is true
only okay so by default it will read
your MD MDC data and put into the format
like in a JSON form key colon value then
key2 colon value like this
okay if you but if you don't want to
read the MDC data you can make it false
so that's the you can say that
what makes MDC
very very critical that our logging
framework log back log 4j2
can read the MDC data what you have
okay can read and also can add into the
log events even though I am just doing
log info whatever the data I have in MDC
that can also come into
the log statement with each log
statement you can say that
so see this in an example so here is the
payment controller I am creating a
logger object with the name payment
controller class. So this would be
creating one logger with com dotconcept
dot payment controller.
Now I have put mdc.put payment id
mdc.put user id. So two keys I have and
I am just doing a normal log statement
log.info.
So what would happen? You know right
internally
this would get converted into event I
logging event
and in this there is one field like MDC
certain context right a certain uh MDC
property map so MDC property map field
is there that will get filled up with
this two values okay then ultimately our
appenders will run okay so here let's
see its appender what we are doing it
Yeah. So the same thing the uh I have 1
2 three appenders and our logger. So our
logger name is com.concepts.p
paymentcontroller. This is the logger
right. Okay. So here I have associated
this logger with three appenders. So all
these three appenders will run. Then the
log statement is accepted. So my logger
level is info and here log statement is
log.info. So this log statement level is
equals or greater than this logger
level. So yes this is accepted and when
this is accepted so all these three
appenders will run.
Okay. So first appender is console with
MDC. Console with MDC. This is the name
print on console and this is the format.
We have already seen that I am using
percentage X payment ID. So only this
P123 will get added. Okay. So here if
you see payment is successful
percentage D date level is info logger
name message hyphen this one. So there
date info logger name message payment is
successful and only the value of the key
payment ID it is coming from the MDC.
So second appender I'm using console
with all MDC. So here this one. So here
I am using percentage X means all values
of the MDC. So here here if you see user
ID and payment id will come both key
equals to value, key equals to value.
And the third appender is console with
JSON. Okay. So here MDC is true. Even if
you don't write it by default it is true
only. Okay. and it's uh encoder is log
stash means in the JSON form it will
come. So here we have already seen in
the structured logging part like these
fields are already defined into log
stash okay encoder but here if you
notice that we are getting this user ID
payment ID in a JSON form
right
so that's the advantage of MDC if you
have certain data in the MDC
then with each with each log statement
those value can be added. Okay. So very
important again I'm saying with each
with each log statement if you have 100
time log.info info log dot error log dot
this with each one
this MDC data is associated and with
each log it can be added into the
output. Okay. So we have to be very very
specific what we are adding into MDC. If
in MDC you have put like thousands of
fields then it's possible that all these
thousand might comes to your with each
log statement which is not even you
wanted
this is not the expectation
okay
but here you might have noticed that
okay sh that's all okay till now we are
good but why you are doing MDC dotclear
here so
why this is I have done to avoid log
pollution. Now this is again a new term.
What is log pollution? In interview when
an interview say that hey how you per
pre prevent lock pollution to happen
very important. So this is nothing but I
told you MDC very heavily used okay
because this only helps in distributed
logging. You will see I told you it's a
per thread
means for one thread let's say thread
one there is one map
one MDC for another thread it has its
own map MDC its own MDC okay now in the
modern system we have something called
thread pool executor
okay in the thread pool we have already
created multiple threads
Okay. And whenever any new requests
come, let's say request one, request
two, request three, they pick one thread
out of this pool and use it. Okay. Now,
it's very very likely that multiple
request
uses the same thread.
So whatever the data request one has put
into the MDC of thread one if you don't
clear it up and if the same thread is
picked by another thread another request
then the log pollution will happen like
so request through is now accessing kind
of the data which is stored by request
one in the MDC
understand with this example. So here I
have a thread pool. I have two thread.
Thread one, thread two. Request one
comes which is for user one. So it ask a
thread pool that give me one thread and
thread one is given to it for the
request A and the thread one. This
thread one MDC has currently user ID
user one and it's performing some task.
Now let's say this task is completed.
Thread is added back to the pool. Now
the request B is coming which is for
user two again ask for thread pool hey
give me one thread again thread one is
given now assume that we haven't done
MDC dotcle we have not done that so mean
this map is still present so here what
this because this MDC map is for per per
thread so this thread is still have
maintain its own MDC which has previous
request data user ID user one but this
is wrong currently request which we are
processing is for user two but it picked
by the same thread we haven't done the
clearer so even for this logs this MDC
data will come user ID user one so log
pollution happened you are processing
request for the user two but in the logs
you will see user one
okay so that's why wherever we have
certain like reusing the thread concept
And generally in modern if you are using
a spring boot definitely by default even
if you don't add there is a by default
thread pull exeutor. So you are reusing
the thread. So it's very important to
clear the MDC as soon as the request
about to finish its work.
Now another important point which
interviewer might ask okay so for each
request I am creating an MDC let's say
and clearing the MDC
and request one so is this safe or
anything need to be handled more yes one
more thing
whenever this task is invoking another
task which is
so ins
let's say this is parent uh parent
thread and this parent thread is
invoking a task which is a singing so it
will create a new thread and I told you
MDC is per thread so when you create a
new thread means new MDC for that thread
so it will not have whatever the parent
has the info in the MDC
So this need to be handled too. So
whenever we create a new thread like at
the rate async your parent thread MDC is
not passed to the child thread. Every
thread has their own MDC. So see this
very simple example
here I have added one payment service
inside that I have a method process
payment which is add the rate nothing
but and in this I am doing log.infoing
info ursing payment process
successfully.
Okay, very simple. And this is a payment
controller. This is the uh method get
payment.
So it has MDC.put MDC.put. So currently
till now main thread is going on. So
this MD this has its own MDC which has
this payment id and user id.
Now what I have done is payment service
do.t process payment. So I am invoking
an ursing method which create a new
thread. So this will create a new
thread.
So I told you that new thread new MDC.
So it has its own MDC.
So this MDC which has this payment ID
user ID is not present here because this
is the new thread. Let's say child
thread it has its own MDC. So when
you're doing log.info info this MDC data
is not copied here with this statement.
So here if you see
for this payment service logger payment
service one I am using this logger name
payment service and this is the appender
I'm using I am using percentage X means
all values which are present inside an
MDC.
So what ultimately you are going
payment process successfully assing
payment process successfully. So this
message is printed successfully.
Percentage X means all the value present
into the MDC. What we got? Hyphen
nothing empty because we have no data
into the MDC. All the data present into
this parent main thread one.
So this is one critical thing which we
have to handle. So how to copy the
parent MDC value to child MDC?
It's asked a lot and even if you are
working you have to deal with it. You
might see in your codebase company code
base there are task decorator.
So that is actually used to copy the
parent MDC to the child MDC.
So this is nothing about a logging
framework. So task decorator is not a
feature of u like logging framework.
It's a normal spring framework generally
I would say. So task decorator is
nothing just a wrapper around the
runnable task. So see this understand
this with an example.
So I'll come to this. So let's
understand with this flow first. So you
have a parent thread. Okay. So you have
a whenever the program is started one
thread is associated first. So let's say
it's a parent thread. Now in the parent
thread what we are doing is we are
invoking payment service.process process
payment. This part payment service dot
process payment. Okay. And this is an
async call. It is invoking an a sync
method.
So what would happen? What is the flow?
So the flow is first proxy will
intercept. Okay. And then it will create
one runnable task. So it will create
this like this runnable task that okay
this task has to be runnable because
this task need to be submitted to Q and
from Q worker thread will pick it up and
run.
So what it will run this it will run
this hey invoke this
okay so currently it's not submitted to
Q and it is not picked by worker thread
currently at this point it create only
runnable task okay now I told you that
task decorator is just a wrapper around
the runnable task okay so the next step
is before it submitted to Q it check if
task decorator not equal this is the
framework code.
So here if you see task decorator not
equals to null, it will first decorate
it. So what it is doing is it accept the
runnable task. Okay. And decorate it. So
now how I am decorating it. See. So this
is my task decorator which it will
trying to invoke. Okay. This is the
method we have to override. Implement
task decorator.
So here currently all happening into the
parent thread itself. So here if you see
currently all happening in the parent
thread. So means I have access to parent
thread MDC.
Okay. So now first it read the MDC from
the parent thread.
Okay. So now this has all the
information.
It's just a map key value map.
Now I am just wrapping
I am just wrapping the runnable. So this
is the actual runnable which we created.
What was the actual runnable? This one.
This is the actual runnable which we
created first. Okay. And I told you that
uh task decorator is just a wrapper
around the runnable text. So this was
the actual
runnable
and we have just added a wrapper. So
first is that if context map is not
equals to null set it. So this is child.
So currently this is just a runnable. So
when who will execute this code
new thread
or you can say that the child thread
okay they will execute this code. So MDC
dots set context map that will get set
for the child one. So this context map
with what info they will get set with
the parent one. So we are taking out the
info from the parent. Okay. And in the
runnable so this is just a runnable not
yet picked by the child. So in the
runnable task so this will get set MDC
dot set. So whichever thread is going to
pick this task
going to start working on this
their MDC will get set with this. Okay.
After that actual runnable what was
that? Run it. Whatever you have to
invoke run it and the finally clear it.
So you see that it's just a wrapper.
Okay. So we are just wrapping this
actual runnable. So above that we are
setting the MDC. After that we are
clearing the MDC. That's all.
So that's all. Okay. So first you create
a runnable and before you try to submit
it what it will do is it will if
decorator is not equals to null it will
call the decorator. So our decorator
will get invoked.
Okay. Then we have just wrapped it
around certain information. What
information? MDC set and after that MDC
clear this is the new runnable which we
have created. Okay. So it return
runnable itself except runnable
return runnable and after that that got
submitted to Q executor Q. From there
worker thread will pick it up and give
it to one thread and that thread what it
will do is it will start executing this
code.
Okay,
it will start executing this code.
So what we have done is that
we have copied the parent MDC to
whatever the thread going to going to
come its MDC like new thread MDC through
task decorator.
Okay. So this is very critical interview
questions when comes and this thread
decorator is nothing related with login
framework. So I just uh told you so that
we get a little context what exactly is
task decorator. So we can write our task
decorator okay and associate it whatever
the thread pool executor you have. So if
you have your custom thread pool
executor we have already covered
threadpool exeutor in depth into the
Java series. So if you have a custom
thread pool executor, you can just set
task decorator and you can add this one
MDC. So currently here I am not setting
it because I don't have my custom
threadpool executor. I am using spring
boot default. So spring boot will
automatically so here if you see it is
using a spring boot default executor. It
automatically set the task decorator MDC
task decorator.
But if you have a custom threadpool
executor in that wherever you have
defined your custom threadpool exeutor
you can set the decorator and just set
MDC the class name that will get set.
Okay. So here
after setting this you can see [snorts]
that async payment process successfully.
Now it got user ID and payment ID.
So this is clear right? So here you can
learn more about this task decorator in
dev. Currently it is not associated with
logging framework. Okay. So this flow I
just showed you so that at least we got
like how parent thread MDC is copied to
a child thread MDC. Okay. So before we
submit the runnable because runnable is
the one which actually run by the new
thread. Before we submit it, everything
is done by parent thread. And that's
where before we submit this runnable
that you have to run this code, we are
have a task decorator and wrap it around
another you can say that we create
another runnable and it's just a wrapper
around the actual runnable.
Okay. So this is the actual runnable and
we just create another runnable. This is
another runnable I'm creating which has
a wrapper like copy the MDC from the
parent and once the actual runnable done
clear it
okay
so now we know what is MDC next we have
to understand what is correlation ID
so here the problem understand one
problem is everything is good till now
so we have our application and this
application multiple requests are coming
and logs goes to let's say we are
creating one file app.log so logs will
go app payment process user created this
is writing certain logs this is calling
some other API which is writing some
other logs request three is calling some
other API which is calling which is
adding some other logs so in our app.log
log. We have so many logs. But how would
you tell which log is added by which
request
now let's say later this query come that
hey this request got failed or why it
got failed. Can you debug? Now you open
the app.log let's say okay you know that
on which date it failed. Okay, I opened
the file for let's say okay for 19th
December I opened the file. Now this
file has thousands of log events. How
would I know that okay this payment
process was done by request three or by
request two or by request one or by
request 100?
We don't know.
So how do you find the log for a
specific request? Say for request one I
want to know this request one has return
what all log event I want to only see
that
that's where correlation ID comes into
the picture.
So correlation ID means for each request
we give one unique ID.
This is unique ID 1, unique ID 2, unique
ID three for each request. And whenever
any log event they are doing okay
log.info
we also add this unique id. So what
happened is like this with every log
event we also have a unique id. So
request one when comes to the
application we created one correlation
ID C1. So C1 correlation ID is nothing
but a unique ID given to a request.
So request one has C1 and whatever the
log events it is generated I am putting
user created C1 okay something payment
process C1. So we know that what all log
events are generated by this request.
Okay. Similarly request two has
correlation ID C2 and whatever the log
it will put it has
this ID attached.
Okay. And now our log aggregator tool
whatever if you are using a data dog or
something if they are reading this file
you you can simply say that hey show me
the logs with ID C1. Now it is very very
easy for it that okay it will just show
you all the log statements which has C1.
So it will show you that only. So now
you can only focus on this log events
and also one thing is that in the
response in the response
we send this. So when you send a
response from the application let's say
for the request one in the header we
send this C1. So that in future if
client say that hey we are facing an
issue with this request its correlation
ID is this C1 developer can ask give me
the correlation ID then only I would be
able to debug
okay so now they will give a correlation
ID yes this is a coalation ID I would go
to the aggregation tool put that hey
fetch me the logs of the C1 what
aggregation tool will do from this huge
logs it has already done indexing and
all So it will only filter out the log
statement which has this C1.
Okay. So this is something very
important that correlation ID.
Okay. And if you want to implement this
the prerequisite is filter. Why filter?
I told you that whenever any request
comes to an application
this request we need to assign one
unique ID. Okay. So we need an entry
point and we need to check at the exit
point so that when request comes we
generate correlation ID and when the
request goes we send the response also
that in the response header this is the
coalition ID let's say. Okay. And which
is the best place for this is filter. So
we have already discussed filter into
the spring boot series. So filter versus
interceptor we have already discussed
and also JWT implementation in the
spring boot. We have used a filter a
lot. So you can get more information
about the filter into JWT authentication
also.
So if you have any doubt about the
filter kindly check out this two videos
in the spring boot series. So very very
quick recap about the filter. It is used
when we want to intercept HTTP request
and response and this was the diagram.
So request comes to our server.
The first thing run is filter chain. So
we need to add one filter. Let's say
this is our filter we have added into
the chain.
Okay. So when the request comes this
filter will run and when the request
goes also then this filter will run.
So now I am doing that. So this is the
normal API I'm writing. This is the log
log.info payment is successful. Okay.
And appender is uh this is my logger
name. Appender is console with all MDC.
So this is the appender encoder pattern.
I am using percentage X means all the
MDC data should be added here. So till
now here I don't have any MDC. Okay. Now
I'm writing my custom filter.
Kindly check out our filter videos then
only you would be clear like currently
I'm not going like what is once per
request filter. We have already
discussed that one. So I'm creating one
filter and in the filter what I am doing
is
if in the request header we have the
correlation ID use that
otherwise create a new unique coalition
ID. You can have any logic. This is just
I showed you an example. If in the
request header coalition ID is present,
use that otherwise create a new
coalition ID and put into MDC. MDC
do.put coalition ID. This is the
coalition ID. And also in the response I
am setting response header set this
coalition ID and proceed with the next
filter. You can have filter change you
have multiple filters. So that's okay.
So what we have done is when request
comes to our filter we have created a
unique ID for the coalition ID if
doesn't exist in the request
then we put into the our MDC
also in the response header and proceed
with the next filter and when the
response will come okay later on finally
when this filter is about to end okay
mdc.clear clear I am doing it
okay so this will run when the response
goes out like so this is the flow let's
say you have a filter request comes then
ultimately your dispatcher sublet your
code then it goes out then again also
filter and then finally out okay so
before it goes out it first run the
finally and it will clear the empty set
okay and you might be saying that hey
why we have to read the header first
generally See this is very important.
Now we are slowly moving into the
distributed logging part. So you have
service one, you have service two. So
here service one is invoking the service
two. Here you have a filter.
Okay. Uh this kind of thing.
Similarly here also we have a filter
should be similar what we have here.
Now when service so this has created a
currently in this request so this is
request one so this is fresh request so
in the request do we have a coalation ID
no so it will generate one so let's say
generate correlation ID one
now when it is invoking the service two
it has to pass this correlation to
service two also because the industry
standard is
if you have multiple service
if the request is coming request one
okay so whatever the log statement goes
here here here
all should have one correlation so let's
say it has generated correlation one so
the all the log statement
which is associated with request one
should have the same correlation
similarly for service two same
correlation
same correlation
So if service one has created this
correlation how it will pass to service
two it will pass this into its request
header. Okay when it invoke it it will
pass into his request header. Now our
filter it filter what it will do. Okay
if header this is present use that
otherwise don't create new. Okay if it
is present don't create new. So it will
reuse the same correlation.
Okay, that's why I put this check.
So this is clear. So why correlation is
important and how we can use a filter to
add a correlation ID into the MDC. Now
what would happen is when you do log
info ultimately appender here percentage
X will try to read from MDC. MDC has
your correlation ID and it will print
that correlation ID got printed with
this log statement.
Okay.
Now the final part how to achieve the
distributed logging. So now we have
covered what is logging, what is uh MDC,
what is your correlation ID. Okay. Now
only thing is that distributed logging
actual distributed logging where we have
multiple microervices and request passes
through let's say service one service
two service three and request passes
through this we have already seen a
glimpse of it okay we can easily achieve
through correlation
so that's what we are going to do but
for that prerequisite is distributed
tracing okay so distributed tracing we
have already covered and distributed
tracing what it does is
when any request come request one comes
into this. So tracing help us to track
the path of a request across
microservices. Okay. First it goes to
this microser then this then this. So
it's path. Okay. So tracing track the
path of request across microser.
For each request unique trace ID is
created.
Okay, so we know which service invoke
which service. But another very
important part is it does not log
detailed events.
So with trace id with trace ID if I put
a trace ID if you remember from the uh
distributed tracing video we have
integrated with Jagger. So if you search
with trace ID you only get that service
one service one invoke service two
service two invoke service five. That is
the request one has
followed the path when it entered
this application. Okay. So this is the
track it followed. But with this trace
ID you can't get okay for service one
what are the logs for service two what
are the logs for service five what are
the logs for this request. So that's
where correlation ID comes into the
picture. Okay. So we have a coalation ID
that
correlation ID 1 coalition ID 1 that
okay yes this is the request in this
service these are the locks okay and
this service these are the logs
coalation one correlation one coalition
one this service these are the logs
coalation one coalition for this request
now one question should come to your
mind hey trace ID is also unique for a
request coalation ID is also unique for
a request why can't they be same
okay why can't they can have a same ID
why we need a different trace ID like
okay I have two ID trace ID correlation
ID with trace ID I am getting this
hierarchy like what path my request was
followed and with correlation ID okay
service one I know that uh it my request
goes to service one then in service one
I am putting correlation ID so trace one
correlation one I am using correlation
ID one to fetch all
Then okay from trace I know that service
two is also involved in this request
flow. I goes to the service two now it's
uses the coalition and fetch all the
logs.
Why can't we have a same ID? Because
they are both unique to a request
itself.
Okay. And with the same ID what my log
aggregation tool will do. It would be
helpful for that also. Hey this is the
trace ID.
T1 for this is for my request R1 search
it. So now log aggregation tool know
that okay this ID is for the flow also I
can get a unique flow what all path this
request has followed plus the log also
have associated with this ID itself
okay so it's easy for them you don't
need to manage two ids
okay so that's what generally most
company does in production
Okay. So I have already told you that
distributed tracing just record track of
the request but no detailed logging.
Whereas correlation ID we have like
detailed logging for each service.
Service one service two in their huge
logging file. We can associate this log
statement is associated with this
correlation ID.
Okay. And I told you that yes both can
be same. Can they be same? Yes. And
that's what big tech company does.
So let's rewind what we have done in
distributed tracing because you will see
that okay whatever done till now
previously
we can easily achieve distributed
logging with that itself. So if you
recall distributed tracing I told you
that distributed tracing has this filter
server HTTP observation filter.
Okay. So if you open this filter
and see what it does is it intercept the
request when it comes. I told you filter
is the one entry point. It intercept the
request
and what it does is it create a new
trace new trace ID
and that time in the distributed tracing
we have not I have not told you but this
not only generate new trace ID but it
also put into the MDC.
So if you are just doing log info
payment is successful
in this log.info info if you are doing
if you are using a structured logging
then this trace ID is automatically
coming in your logs so you don't
specifically need a filter
for correlation
ID you don't have to worry about that I
need to generate a unique ID for the
correlation because anyway you need
tracing if you have a distributed micros
service you have multiple services okay
Then definitely you need a tracing to
determine this request goes through
which all services otherwise you won't
know what all services are involved
which all services is failed in the path
that will automatically take care of
adding a unique ID into the MDC and when
you do log.info info
this trace ID which is added into MDC
got also attached to this one when you
put the log and the same thing you can
use to filter out okay so that's what
the advantage I am using for the tracing
that we don't need to add custom filter
okay uh so we don't have to worry about
correlation ID because unique ID which
is for a request trace ID is already
present into MDC
and also So we don't have to pass the
collation ID in request harder. I told
you that when service one service 2
service one is invoking service two in
the request header you need to pass the
coalation ID so that whatever the logs
for this request
this service 2 is creating they will
also have the same coalition. So this
log is also like coalition ID1 coalition
ID1 coalition ID1. So this also has
correlation ID one same correlation
generally this is industry standard
multiple service for same request same
correlation ids all
uh component has so how this is achieved
in the request header you are passing
the correlation ID which they are using
it they are not creating new and in the
distributed tracing we have already seen
[snorts] in the distributed tracing
video we have already seen
that trace ID is automatically present
present into the request header. Okay.
So when service one invoke service two
in the request header trace ID is
automatically added.
So when the service to receive this
request they also pass to server HTTP
observation filter because in
distributed microservices we have to use
tracing.
So this filter exists and will this
filter exist what it will check it will
intercept the request if the header
request header contains the trace ID it
will not create new it will reuse it the
same logic okay and after that it will
put into MDC.
So both the things are working
with distributed tracing both things are
working. Why? Because distributed
tracing what they are doing is
when the request come they have an
interceptor
they are catching it they are for this
request one they are creating a trace ID
okay and when this got invoked service
got invoked in the request header this
trace ID is also getting passed so that
is all fine this is all done till
tracing but one thing we
didn't I didn't tell you in the
distributed tracing it also put into
MDC. So in MDC also it put that this is
the trace ID one. So what happened
because of MDC is that whatever the logs
this service is writing for this request
they will also got this unique trace ID
and that's what we want. We want to
attach a unique ID with the log.
Okay. And this
unique trace id automatically get passed
to with the tracing it goes to the
request header and there also it has a
filter and it will check that okay if
the request has the trace ID it will use
the it will it will not create new trace
ID it will use the same trace ID and it
will also put into the MDC. So its log
also will have the same ID.
Okay. But still,
but still you will see that many
companies
still write a filter for the correlation
ID.
Why?
There are two reason. One thing is we
need to send the correlation ID in the
response header. So we can have our own
filter for coalation ID and in that we
can add it into the response header like
here I am doing it. So here if you see
coalition ID filter I am adding into the
response.
Okay that is one advantage. The second
advantage is what if tracing is
disabled. What if your company says that
hey we don't want tracing at all.
then your correlation logic would break
also because now you hardly depend on
okay trace ID is present
and then only I would be reusing it.
So we still have correlation filter. So
see this one example. So now we are
using tracing also distributed tracing.
So in the distributed tracing these
three dependency we wanted so I have
added it. Kindly check out the
distributed tracing video if you have
any doubt. If you think that I'm going
fast, it's because we have already
covered distributed tracing. So I have
added the dependency in pom.xml
and in application.properties I have
added like this is our Jagger
uh endpoint. Okay. So my Jagger is
already started. This is the endpoint
and this is my application name.
Now this is very simple controller class
like when this endpoint is hit it is
just doing log.info
and return successfully. That's all. No
uh trace ID correlation ID logic here.
Nothing no MDC nothing. It's very simple
like how in the production you are
seeing.
Now all the game is inside the filters.
So since we have added this tracer
tracing into our application. So we have
a micrometer and open telemetry. So this
filter is bring by micrometer.
So what this micrometer will do when the
request comes
it will intercept the request. Now let's
say we have like service one invoke
service 2. Request is coming to service
one.
So first it will goes to this server
HTTP observation filter. Does request
has any trace ID? No. This is the fresh
request coming. So it will create one
trace ID.
So this filter is already we have we
don't have to write that filter that
comes with the micrometer. So and also
it will put into the MDC also. So we
have a trace id
something like a trace ID and some T1
into the MDC. It's already present now.
Okay. Now it's a filter chain right? So
now our filter will run also. So all
custom filter run later. Okay. So now
our filter will run what I have put a
logic that
so tracer I am using a tracer. If you
haven't seen the tracer uh distributed
tracing video you might find it
difficult. So kindly check it out. So
generally this is the uh you can say
that class which we can use to fetch the
trace ID.
So tracer.curren.context.trace
ID. So I am fetching out the trace id.
Hey if there is already a trace ID
created or not because if it is
then I am not creating a new ID for my
correlation but let's say in future
tracer is disabled so what ID I will get
unique ID null if it is null then only I
am creating a new ID so my correlation
filter will always work so whatever the
log events will come it will always have
unique ID if trace if trace ID is
present it will use that if that trace
ID is let's say disabled or tracer is
removed tracing is removed from your
application still we will generate one
unique ID for the collation
so for now we have tracer enabled in our
application okay we have a tracer
enabled so trace ID is present so what
I'm doing is that yes take out the trace
ID if it is not null okay then we don't
have to create a new ID we are just
putting MDC doput correlation ID So in
the MDC we also put correlation ID also
the same trace ID T1.
Okay.
And also in the response I am setting
that okay I want to send into the
response also that in future if they
have they want developer to debug they
can pass us the correlation ID and we
can sort out the logs. Okay. So here in
the response
here I have shown here somewhere in the
response. Yeah in the response
we can return like this
whatever the coalition ID or trace ID
you are putting.
Okay. So I'm setting into the response.
Okay. And finally MDC.clear. So now all
the filters run. Ultimately the control
goes to our
controller where is got this one
controller.
Now it's doing payment is successful.
Now when payment is successful
so logger appender will come because
this only has to print. So I'm using
pattern not JSON one. So here I have
percentage X means whatever the data
present into MDC. So in MDC what we have
trace ID coalition ID which is should be
same. So here if you see it's in
this one we have trace ID 9 E7D
something coalition ID 9 E70 something.
Okay. So even though trace ID is present
into the MDC we are still adding
coalition ID which is generally same. So
we are not generating a new we are
reusing the same unique ID for the
request
and it's just an advantage for the coal
uh log aggregation tool
that okay if you search with this ID
they can do both the things first with
this ID they can track the path okay
s_sub_1 s_ub_2 then s3 and with the same
ID itself
they can fetch is the logs also for this
request.
Okay. And here if you see I don't have
to worry about that. Okay. If I created
an another application
service 2 what I have to do everything
is taken care. Why? Because service 2 is
also going to be same. In service two
distributed tracing we have to enable.
So the filter will automatically come
this filter. Okay. And when service one
invoke service two automatically this
micrometer pass in the request header
this trace ID.
Now it service 2 this filter what it
will do is it intercept the request. If
the trace ID is present into the header
it won't create new. So it filter
already put MDC
trace ID the unique trace ID whatever it
is created T1. Okay.
And the same filter we will add into
into service two also the same
correlation filter. Okay. So there what
would happen if the trace ID is present
which is already it don't create a
unique coalition ID. It will use the
same trace ID and put it. So with the
same code into the another service
will work out of the box.
Okay. And we have achieved the
distributed logging.
We have an ID through which we can track
the path of the request
and we have the unique ID within each
log statement
which our log aggregation tool like data
dog
can use it. So this is now the task of
the log aggregation tool data do we have
just posted the let's say file inside
this log events we have just associated
with each log event a unique ID t1 let's
say t1 t1 okay now it's up to log
aggregation tool like data dog they need
to do certain filtering indexing
whatever they are doing whatever their
logic would be all we have to do is in
their search tool we have to just put t1
okay and okay I am looking for a field
let's say trace ID T1 because in our
logs trace ID is also there. So if you
search with this trace ID again this log
aggregation tool would be able to show
the event in a particular service. If
you also search with correlation ID and
give this again this log aggregation
tool would be able to show all the logs
which has this correlation one in the
particular service. So you can search
with either trace ID, you can search
with coalition ID because that our logs
each log statement has both. So log
aggregation tool should be able to parse
it and do certain indexing or not.
Okay. But our work is still here. If we
are clear with this, we understand
distributed logging.
I hope it is clear that
how distributed tracing helps in
achieving distributed logging.
Okay, any doubt let me know. I know this
is too much information and distributed
logging is huge concept. Okay, I tried I
covered all the subtopics. If you have
any doubt, we can discuss into the
comment section. But kindly go through
this video again. Okay, first check out
all the prerequisite distributed tracing
revise it so that when you are going
through this distributed logging right
what trace ID and what is server http
observation filter does what we are
doing here things will become
automatically clear
okay all you have to do is that rewind
the previous one and just rewatch it
you would be able to connect the dots.
Okay, but yes, this is industry standard
distributed logging. Okay, guys, bye.